### **USMAN SALEEM**

Tel: (+61)04 5058 9445 Email: <u>usman@usmans.info</u> Website: <u>www.usmans.info</u>

#### **PROFILE**

A driven and exceptionally talented Architect with expertise in the leadership and management of numerous projects, utilising business and technical translation techniques to effectively complete all aspects of the project including the use of programming, analytical and development skills. An individual with the ability to build and manage key business partnerships, overseeing client specifications and managing all costs and timescales, skills and experience that would enhance any forward thinking organisation.

#### **EXPERTISE**

- Architect Expertise
- Extensive Project Management Experience
- Client Relationships
- Team Leadership and Coaching
- Understanding Business Objectives
- Business and Technical Translation
- Extensive Academic Knowledge
- Building Key Business Partnerships
- Extensive Multi Site Experience
- Extensive Global Experience

- Web Development and Management
- Managing Complex Projects
- Java JEE Expertise
- Software Solutions
- Architecture Frameworks
- Online Technology
- Budget Control
- Business Strategy Delivery
- Technical Expertise
- Stakeholder Relationships

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### 07/2013 – To Date Software Engineer III – Ventyx Responsibilities

- Utilizing technical and analytical skills in developing Ventyx' next generation of Laboratory Information Management System (LIMS)
- Following Scrum and Agile methodology and using Model driven approach and Java/JEE/Flex/RSA tools and technologies.

#### **Technologies**

Java, Flex, HTML, JBoss 5/7 AS, Hibernate, Databases (Oracle), Spring, Model Driven Development, UML (IBM Rational Software Architect), continuous integration (Jenkins)

# 01/2012 – 07/2013 Senior Technical Support Engineer – Red Hat Asia Pacific Pty Ltd. Responsibilities

- Provide front line technical assistance to ensure that customers get the most out of JBoss products
- Engage and collaborate with open source developers
- Offer developer-to-developer assistance for the JBoss Enterprise Middleware Suite
- Work alongside in-house developers, suggest fixing & improving code, provide technical solutions and contribute to the JBoss & open source software communities
- Provide guidance to customers over the phone
- Expertise in specific JBoss technologies. EJB Deployers, HornetQ, SQL and Transactions, Clustering, Security
- Interaction with customers advising them architectural design decisions

#### **Technologies**

JBoss EAP/AS 5/6/7, HornetQ, EJB, Servlets, JSP

# 11/2010 – 12/2011 Software Architect – OpenSCG Inc, USA Responsibilities

- Engaged with USA based clients using On-Site/Off-Site model. Projects involving rearchitecture of JEE and PostgreSQL based projects for horizontal scalability and reducing performance bottlenecks, resulting in increase of transactions throughput and capability of handling millions of users concurrently with optimal response time.
- RPM and DEB packages development for OpenJDK and PostgreSQL distributions.
- Provided customized CRM implementation, reporting servers and improving user security in existing implementation of open source mailing lists manager by managing and interacting remote clients.

#### **Technologies**

Java, JDBC, EJB, JEE, Jasper Server, CiviCRM, Smarty Templates, Resin Caucho, Tomcat, JBoss, SubethaMail, Funambol (Mobile Cloud Computing), Google Web Toolkit, Android 2.x, Spring, PostgreSQL 9.0, HornetQ, Amazon Web Services (S3, EC2, SQS), PostgreSQL RPM/DEB installers, Scrum

# 02/2004 – 10/2010 Architect – EnterpriseDB PK (SMC-Pvt) Ltd, Pakistan Responsibilities

- Direct responsibility for utilising leadership and technical skills in the overseeing of all projects including the design and development of software solutions, utilising expertise within Java/ J2EE, open source and cross platform technologies
- Built and managed key client relationships during the management of all projects and tasks, working on site through the accurate analysis of existing infrastructure and rearchitecture of database model
- Managed numerous technical projects including the Postgres Plus Advanced Server suite of installers, integrating framework on MAC OS X, Linux 64, Linux 32 and windows operating system
- Ensured the excellent leadership of colleagues, working continually in line with project and client objectives and utilising excellent global experience
- Completed effective numerous projects within budget and timescales including the re-architect EnterpriseDB Redwood Replicator Project and the EnterpriseDB Management Server Project
- Continually analysed cutting edge technologies, recommending improvements to enhance efficiency
- Selected to join the team responsible for building a J2EE based grid infrastructure for use within stores, utilised extensive technical knowledge including ANT, AXIS, Hibernate, XDoclet, JUnit, JBoss AS and EJB
- Successfully promoted throughout career within the organisation, initially joining as an Associate
  Consultant and progressing to Consultant Software Engineer, Senior Software Engineer, Associate
  Architect and Architect

#### **Technologies**

Java, J2EE, Struts, Hibernate, RMI, Swing, JDBC, EJB, ANT, Apache AXIS, Apache DBCP, JUnit, PostgreSQL, EnterpriseDB AS and Installer frameworks

# 01/2002 – 01/2004 Senior Web Developer – College of eCommerce USA, Pakistan Responsibilities

- Selected to Design and develop the company's web portal, overseeing all technical aspects including domains, email hosting and J2EE applications for over 30 institutes within the campus
- Responsibility for the overall design of the student management system, utilising expertise within Java/ J2EE, enabling the analysis of student results on a remote basis
- Successfully created and managed the company's web portal including an online site management system, working with Active Server Pages
- Direct responsibility for the management of all technical matters including the creation of an online testing system, providing technical expertise and guidance throughout the transition period

#### **Technologies**

Java 1.3, Servlets, JSP, ASP, Tomcat and IIS

### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Java Technologies: Java 1.3-1.7, Swing, RMI, JDBC, JNI, Java Web Start, etc.

JEE Technologies: Servlets, JSP, EJB 2/3, J2EE 1.4, JEE 5/6, JNDI, LDAP

Framework/Libraries: Struts 1, 2, Hibernate, Apache AXIS, Apache Commons, Jasper Reports, Jasper Server, Spring, HornetQ, GWT,

Amazon Web Services, Android etc.

**Tools:** IBM Rational Software Architect (RSA), Ant, Maven, Gradle,

Git, CVS, NetBeans, Eclipse, IntelliJ IDEA, Together 6.0, Rational Rose 2000, pgAdmin, Bitrock, Installshield, Install

Anywhere, WiX, RPM/DEB

Platforms: Databases (PostgreSQL, Oracle, EnterpriseDB, SQL Server,

MySQL, HSQLDB), OS (Linux, Mac OSX, Windows), Application Servers (JBoss 4-7, Tomcat 5/6, Jetty, Resin

Caucho, JRun)

**Design Skills:** OOA (Object Oriented Analysis) & OOD (Object Oriented

Design), MDD (Model Driven Development), Design by

Contract, GoF Design Patterns, JEE design patterns, and UML

Other: Bash scripting, SQL, .NET framework, C#, ASP, ASP.NET,

Visual C++, ANSI C, gcc, MingW, Dreamweaver MX, Gimp

### **PUBLICATIONS**

**Developer.com** - "A patter/framework for Client/Server programming in Java" <a href="http://www.developer.com/java/ent/article.php/1356891">http://www.developer.com/java/ent/article.php/1356891</a> (2002) discussed a pattern/framework for programs that are developed using client/server methodology. Provide a successfully implemented framework for developing Internet enabled applications

**Developer.com** - "Using XML as application level protocol"

http://www.developer.com/xml/article.php/1380861 (2002) Demonstrated ability to use XML as application level protocol while developing network enabled applications. Discusses the pros and cons of XML as application level protocol

**Developer.com** - "Stopping a class from being inherited in Java, the Official way and the unofficial way." <a href="http://www.developer.com/java/other/article.php/3109251">http://www.developer.com/java/other/article.php/3109251</a> (2003) discussed two techniques to stop a class from being inherited and how to use private constructor to stop inheritance mechanism in Java

**Developer.com** - "Developing Java Web Services with AXIS" <a href="http://www.developer.com/services/article.php/3443951">http://www.developer.com/services/article.php/3443951</a> (2004) discussed how to customise AXIS to develop Java based web services rapidly and hassle-free

### **EDUCATION & QUALIFICATIONS**

2012 Red Hat Certified System Administrator

2006 Sun Certified Web Component Developer for Java 2 EE 1.4 2006 Sun Certified Business Component Developer for Java 2 EE 1.3

2005 Sun Certified Developer for Java 2 platform

2003 MSc in Computer Sciences (Silver Medallist) – Mohammad Ali Jinnah University

(Islamabad Campus)

2002 Sun Certified Programmer for Java 2 platform 1.2

1998 Bachelor of Commerce (First Division) – Punjab College of Commerce affiliated with

The University of Punjab